Okay today we pick up on דף פ"ט עמוד ב' Daf Pey-Tet
Amud Bet 89b in גיטין Gittin and we wrap up yesterday's דף
Daf and then we will do צ' Tzadi the last דף Daf
of גיטין. Gittin. So we are in the middle of פ"ט עמוד
ב' Pey-Tet Amud Bet and אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi it
is about 20 lines down
if you go where the תוספות Tosafot says אמר רב הונא Amar
Rav Huna and you go across from there and you go up
about five lines. Lines start with the word רבנן. Rabbanan. אמר רב
אשי Amar Rav Ashi and we're in the middle of a discussion
here in the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna spoke about if there
is a rumor, a קול, Kol, that a woman got married, we
have to be concerned about that and not allow her to marry
somebody else without a גט Get from the person she was rumored
to be married to, but then there's a lot of discussion in
the גמרא Gemara about exactly the situations in which that's true. First
of all we wouldn't pay attention to such rumors after a woman
was already married, rumors about her status, that's קול אחר נישואין. Kol
Achar Nisuin. Also issues about how much type of substantiation there has
to be about that rumor, that actually there's a lot of supporting
type of circumstances and supporting evidence and there was a whole question
about the degree that you need that and then there was another
question also about whether we're מבטלינן קלא, Mevatlinan Kala, whether when we
find out that the קול Kol was false do we proactively go
and try to, you know, and try to negate it so that
and make sure that it's not out there as an issue to
be concerned about, or if we find out, I should say, that
the קול Kol was not substantiated. So a lot of really important
questions, very hard to quantify some of these things and now we
pick up with this with אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. אמר
רב אשי כל קול דלא אתחזק בבי דינא לאו קולא הוא. Amar
Rav Ashi kol kol d'lo it-chazek b'vei dina lav kola hava. Any
קול, Kol, any type of a rumor that the בית דין Beis
Din has not looked into it and established that this is something
to be concerned about, would not be something that we would be
concerned about. Okay which is somewhat consistent with the idea before that
you need substantiating evidence and so on and here he is saying
that really it's a reinforcing of that idea. If you look at
רש"י Rashi here the first wide רש"י Rashi says לא חיישינן ליה
אלא אם כן ידעו בית דין העיר שכך יצא קול פלוני מהיכן
שמע וגזרו שיחושו לקול זה Lo chashinan lei ela im ken yadu
be-vei din ha-ir she-kach yatza kol ploni mehichan shama ve-gazru she-yeichushu le-kol
zeh that the בית דין Beis Din has to first of all
investigate based on standards that we had discussed earlier in the גמרא
Gemara and they actually declared yes this is a קול Kol to
be concerned about. Okay ואמר רב אשי Va-amar Rav Ashi and similarly
רב אשי Rav Ashi said כל קול דבתר נישואין לא חיישינן ליה
Kol kol d'vasar nisuin lo chashinan lei and this is something that
we had said earlier, any קול Kol that comes after the woman
is married, after she got married there was a rumor that she
was, let's say, had sex beforehand and makes her forbidden to a
כהן Kohen or was married to some other man or something of
that nature, we're not concerned about that, we're not going to pay
attention to it once it has an impact on the man that
she is married to, on her current status. So the
גמרא Gemara says דבתר אירוסין חיישינן ליה D'vasar erusin chashinan lei and
but that would mean that if it came after אירוסין, Erusin, not
when she is already living with this man but only has had
קידושין Kiddushin with that man, then that would be something that we'd
be concerned about and we would have to act accordingly again assuming
that it satisfied all the requirements of a קול. Kol. רב חביבא
אמר אפילו דבתר אירוסין נמי לא חיישינן ליה Rav Chaviva amar afilu
d'vasar erusin nami lo chashinan lei and רב חביבא Rav Chaviva says
no we're not even concerned with that because again it will have
implications on this man that she's already married to, it's not just
a generic question of her status, there's actually a relationship here that
is being impacted.
והלכתא לא חיישינן ליה Ve-hilkheta lo chashinan lei and we rule like
רב חביבא Rav Chaviva that once there is, she is married to
a man, we are not concerned about those types of rumors. Okay
אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא שדרוה מבי רב לשמואל, Amar Rav Yirmeya
bar Abba shakhluhu mi-bei Rav le-Shmuel, they sent from the house of
רב Rav to שמואל, Shmuel, ילמדנו רבינו, Yelamdeinu Rabbeinu, let our master
teach us, יצא לה קול מראשון ובא אחר וקידשה קידושי תורה מהו.
Yatza lah kol mei-rishon u-va acher ve-kiddesha kiddushei Torah mahu. Okay so
this is going to be an actually a case of קול Kol
and then there was somebody and you know normally we say once
there's a קול Kol then like here's the procedure you have to
be חושש Choshesh you should do this you shouldn't do that but
here somebody just went ahead and acted despite the קול. Kol. So
there was a קול Kol that she was married to ראובן Reuven
and then שמעון Shimon came along and married her in a way
in front of everybody, קידושי תורה Kiddushei Torah meaning it wasn't just
a קול Kol people saw שמעון Shimon come ahead and give her
קידושין Kiddushin and said הרי את מקודשת לי Harei at mekudeshet li
and so on in disregard of the קול Kol and presumably this
was a type of a קול Kol
that
normally we would be concerned about. Okay מהו? Mahu? So what should
we do? שלח להו תצא. Shalach le-hu teitzei. She has to leave
the second guy
where meaning presumably it sounds like a גט Get but we'll sort
of see in a minute. She has to be concerned about the
קול. Kol. It was a type of a קול Kol presumably you'd
be concerned about. והעמידו הדבר על בוריו Ve-ha-amidu ha-davar al buryo but
try to establish the actual
fact. or מאי היא *Mai hi* or מאי ועמידו דבר davar, על
בוריו *Mai v'amidu davar al buryo*, what does it mean that we
should clarify the matter? So the first position is we're חושש *chochesh*
for the קול kol *kol* even בדיעבד bedieved *be'diavad* and even if
she married, the second guy did קידושין Kidushin *kiddushin*, we force the
second guy to divorce her. That's what it sounds like. Okay, and
now you're going to clarify it, so what does that mean? אילימא
דמגלי מילתא דקידושי קמא לאו קידושי מעליא נינהו *Ilima de'megali milta de'kiddushei
kama lav kiddushei ma'alya ninhu*, so if it means that we're going
to investigate and then we're going to identify and find out that
the first one actually was not valid. Okay, it was enough of
a קול kol *kol* that there was something to be concerned about,
let's say it was the case in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, everybody
came out and they were carrying candles and everybody was talking oh
my gosh what a beautiful wedding that was, etc., but you didn't
have actual formal עדות *eidus*. Okay, so that was a pretty strong
קול kol. *kol* and now we're going to look into it and
we're going to say that and we're going to see oh you
know what guess what the ring wasn't a שווה פרוטה *shaveh prutah*
or something, it wasn't a good קידושין Kidushin *kiddushin*. So therefore and
if you look into it and determine that the first one was
not something to be worried
about מבטלינן קלא *mevatlinan kala* and therefore we would go ahead and
we would actually say okay fine actually we looked into it it's
not a concern and the second guy does not have to divorce
her. If that's what you mean, stage number one assume the קול
kol, *kol* is true, there was good substantiating circumstances, but check into
it, if you determine it was not true then you can ignore
it and move on. But you can't say that. והא נהרדעא אתריה
דשמואל הוא *V'ha Neharde'a atreih de'Shmuel hu*, but נהרדעא *Neharde'a* was the
place of
שמואל *Shmuel* and actually I don't know why they said that, they
actually explicitly they sent to שמואל *Shmuel*. והא נהרדעא אתריה דשמואל הוא
ולא מבטלינן קלא *V'ha Neharde'a atreih de'Shmuel hu v'lo mevatlinan kala*, and
שמואל *Shmuel* and נהרדעא *Neharde'a* meaning נהרדעא
*Neharde'a* we know is the place that is not מבטל *mevatel* the
קול kol *kol*. Okay, so therefore now by the way that's interesting
you see that בית דין Beit Din *beis din* finds out that
it really was not a problem and still they would not be
מבטל *mevatel* the קול kol. *kol*, which means that at a certain
point if there's enough substantiating circumstances and so on, בית דין Beit
Din *beis din* can't rule in a way or allow a practice
in a way that seems according to everybody to violate their clear
understanding of the reality. It's this point that the only difference between
reality and perception is it's a lot easier to change reality than
perception. So even if בית דין *beis din* determines that the קול
kol. *kol* was false, they're going to force the second if you
פסקן pasken *pasken* like נהרדעא *Neharde'a* and which is where שמואל's *Shmuel's*
place which is that you're not מבטל *mevatel* the קול kol *kol*,
then you're going to still force the second guy to give a
גט get *get* because everybody's going to think that he's married to
this woman who's married to another man. So therefore that can't be.
אלא ela דמגלי מילתא דקידושי קמא קידושי מעליא נינהו *Ella de'megali milta
de'kiddushei kama kiddushei ma'alya ninhu*, oh but okay so what it means
clarify the matter is now you just have some קול kol *kol*
that she is married to the first guy with some
supporting circumstances, but now you go ahead and you investigate and you
speak to people that were there and you get direct testimony that
it was
true. In that case לא צריכה גט get משני *lo tzricha get
mi'sheni*, then she doesn't need a גט get. *get* from the second
guy, then she can actually go ahead and stay married to the
first guy. So here's the ruling: the ruling is okay with it's
a strong קול kol *kol*, so she might be married to the
first guy so you have to force the second guy to give
a גט get *get*. Now go ahead and investigate. If you investigate
and find out that she was never married to the first guy,
it doesn't matter, the קול kol *kol* is the קול kol *kol*
and the second guy's going to have to give the גט get
*get*. Okay fine, she can't be married to the second guy. But
if you find out that the first guy she definitely was married
to him, it's not just a קול kol *kol*, it's a fact,
in that case then the second guy doesn't even need to give
her a גט get *get*, she just goes back to she just
is married to the first guy. So the ruling תצא tetzei, *teitzei*
is true regardless. The second guy cannot she cannot stay married to
the second guy because the קול kol *kol* is the קול *kol*
whether it's proven to be true or not. Okay, whether she needs
a גט get *get* or not from the second guy is based
on whether you have evidence or you just have a קול *kol*
in terms of her marriage to the first guy.
All right, ופליגא דרב
הונא *U'pliga de'Rav Huna*, this argues on רב הונא Rav Huna, *Rav
Huna* דאמר רב הונא Rav Huna, *da'amar Rav Huna* אשת איש שפשטה
ידה וקיבלה קידושין Kidushin מאחר מקודשת mekudeshes *eishes ish she'pash'ta yadah v'kibla
kiddushin me'acher mekudeshes* מדרב המנונא *mi'deRav Hamnuna* that רב הונא Rav Huna,
*Rav Huna* says that if a married woman sticks out her hand,
she's married to ראובן Reuven. *Reuven*, we know she's married to ראובן
Reuven, *Reuven*, and she goes out and she accepts קידושין Kidushin *kiddushin*
from שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, okay then she is married to שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* based on the teaching of רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna's *Rav Hamnuna*
דאמר רב המנונא *da'amar Rav Hamnuna* האשה שאמרה לבעלה גירשתני נאמנת חזקה
אין אשה מעיזה פניה בפני בעלה *ha'ishah she'amra l'ba'alah geirashtani ne'emenes chazaka
ein ishah me'izah paneha bifnei ba'alah* that if a woman says straight
to her husband's face you have divorced me she is believed, we
think that a woman would never be that brazen to say that
in the presence of her husband if it were not true and
therefore accepting קידושין Kidushin *kiddushin* from שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is like saying
directly to her husband that you divorced me. So were we to
פסקן pasken. *pasken* that way, that's exactly this case is that
she accepted. קידושין Kidushin. from ראובן. Reuven, So, therefore, says the גמרא,
Gemara that
according to that, she would definitely and now whether it means, you
know, whether that teaching by the way of רב הונא, Rav Huna
he said, you know, would say that means that she can even
she doesn't need a גט get from the first guy or she's
חוששין chosheshin that she's מקודשת to the שני sheni whatever. But anyway,
we see there that even if there's known as a fact that
she's married to ראובן, Reuven. she still is going to minimally need
a גט get, from the second guy. And here we're saying that
if you determine as a fact that she's married to ראובן, Reuven.
she doesn't she can just go back to ראובן. Reuven. She doesn't
need a גט. get So, the גמרא Gemara says, no. ואידך, Ve-idach,
the response back would be כי אימת דרב המנונא בפניו שלא בפניו
מזה ומזה. Ki imat de-Rav Hamnuna be-fanav she-lo be-fanav mi zeh u-mi
zeh. No, no, no, no, no. רב המנונא statement was only if
she says directly to her husband, "You divorced me," or if she
accepts the קידושין kidushin from שמעון Shimon. in the presence of her
husband. That's when we give credence to the fact that it must
be that she really is divorced. Okay, but in this case, she
accepted קידושין from שמעון Shimon? not in the presence of ראובן. Reuven.
So, again to repeat, okay, this woman, there's a קול that she
was married to ראובן. Reuven, She accepts קידושין from שמעון Shimon not
in the presence of ראובן. Reuven The הלכה halacha is the קול
is a strong קול. She can't stay married to שמעון. Shimon. Does
she have to get a גט get from שמעון? Shimon, If there's
just a קול, she has to get a גט get from שמעון
Shimon. because we don't know if the קול'ס kol's true or not.
But if we know for a fact she was married ראובן, Reuven?
she doesn't have to get a גט Get from שמעון. Shimon. How
about the fact that even a woman who we know is married
ראובן Reuven's who accepts קידושין from שמעון, Shimon we say that that's
like evidence that she's divorced so from ראובן? Reuven's The answer's no.
It's only evidence if it was in ראובן Reuven, presence. This was
not in ראובן Reuven's presence, and therefore, she doesn't even need a
גט Get from שמעון. Shimon תוספות, Tosafos, by the way, points out
that we all agree that to really consider it as evidence that
she was divorced from ראובן, Reuven's it has to be in ראובן
Reuven, presence. That was never debated. But the point here is once
you start with that, maybe, you know, we would at least concede
that even not in ראובן Reuven's presence she should need a גט
Get from שמעון. Shimon And the answer is no, that if you
know for a fact she was married to ראובן, Reuven. and even
when she accepts the קידושין from שמעון Shimon. not in ראובן Reuven.
presence, then that is meaningless, and she doesn't need a גט, Get
and it says nothing, and she just goes back to being married
with to ראובן. Reuven. Okay, very good.
Okay, now, לא מצא דבר ברור ומה הוא. Lo matza davar barur
ve-ma hu. Okay, now, back to our case. We've investigated it and
you don't know what the story is. Okay, there was a room
a strong קול she was married to ראובן. Reuven שמעון Shimon. gave
her קידושין. You investigated it, you don't know one way or the
other, you're left where you were. So, until now it sounded like,
you know, we said basically שמעון Shimon would have to divorce her,
and presumably, she'd go back to be married to ראובן. Reuven, But
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says, or, you know, according to
the קול. So, the גמרא Gemara says, לא מצא דבר ברור ומה
הוא. Lo matza davar barur ve-ma hu. What's the story?
אמר רב הונא מגרש ראשון ונושא שני. Amar Rav Huna megaresh rishon
ve-nosei sheni. ומגרש שני ונושא ראשון לא. U-megaresh sheni ve-nosei rishon lo.
The opposite of what the language said, the language was תצא, tetzei
but he's explaining תצא tetzei meaning תצא from the first guy. ראובן
Reuven actually has to be the one to divorce her and now
she can, if she chooses so, she can be married to שמעון.
Shimon, Right? Because we're concerned about the קול. So, one way of
dealing with the קול is if if according to the קול she's
married with ראובן, Reuven. let ראובן Reuven, divorce her and let her
go be married to שמעון. Shimon Okay, what about the switch? You
know, that's what we'd sort of assumed, that let שמעון Shimon, divorce
her and let her go back and be married to ראובן. Reuven
Even if if the קול was true, that certainly would be the
case, and even if the קול weren't true, that could be okay.
So, he says, no,
ומגרש שני ונושא ראשון לא. U-megaresh sheni ve-nosei rishon lo. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? Why? אתי למימר מחזיר גרושתו מן האירוסין. Asi le-meimar machzir
grushaso min ha-irusin. Because people will say, "Oh, you know what? Both
what happened was was that the קול is true, she was married
to ראובן, Reuven. then ראובן Reuven, divorced her, then she got married
to שמעון, Shimon now שמעון Shimon, is divorcing her, and now she's
going back to being married with ראובן." Reuven. So, we don't like
the perception of that. Okay, so even though there's no קול right
now about a divorce from ראובן, Reuven, we are not going to
let that be an option, which really feels very unfortunate. You know,
anytime we sort of give in to the perception of the crowd,
you know, when even if we're covering our bases, feels like to
be unfortunate. So, okay, we're concerned about the possibility she's married to
ראובן. Reuven That should give us our options
open. ראובן, Reuven. you know, they'll have to figure it out between
the three of them, but at least we have the options of
ראובן Reuven divorcing her and being married to שמעון, Shimon or שמעון
Shimon divorcing her and being married ראובן. Reuven, Either way will work
whatever the reality of the קול is. But we're going to say,
"No, no, no, we're concerned about the perception that a ראובן Reuven,
marriage was then..." existed and there'll be a perception of divorce and
then we marry.
Okay, that's his position. ושנינא בריה דרב אידי אמר אף מגרש שני
ונושא ראשון. V'shinana breih d'Rav Idi amar af megarish sheini venosei rishon.
No, he's okay with that. The second guy can divorce and marry
the first one. We're not concerned that there'll be another layer and
say that there was a marriage to ראובן, Reuven a divorce, a
marriage to שמעון, Shimon a divorce, and now מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso.
מימר אמרי איני רבנן בקידושי וקידושי טעות הוה, Meimar amri inei rabbanan
bekidushi vekidushei taus hava, that the rabbis looked into it and discovered
that it was an error,
that the,
once she winds up going back to ראובן, Reuven rather than saying,
oh, שמעון Shimon. divorced her, and then saying she was married to
ראובן Reuven and then married to שמעון Shimon and divorced and remarried,
etc., they'll say the reason she's going back to ראובן Reuven. is
because she was always married to ראובן Reuven, because the marriage to
שמעון Shimon was never good. Okay,
so now again to review. There was a rumor that she was
married to ראובן. Reuven, It was a strong rumor. Then she went
ahead and she got married to שמעון. Shimon. So because we're concerned
with the rumor, we can't just leave the situation like it is.
We go ahead and we first we try to verify what the
reality is. If we have evidence that she's married to ראובן, Reuven.
then fine, then whatever happened with שמעון Shimon was meaningless,
she stays with ראובן, Reuven we're not concerned that accepting קידושין from
שמעון Shimon signifies something about her relationship with ראובן. Reuven That's good.
If we determine that the rumor was definitely false, doesn't help us.
לא מבטלינן קלא. Lo mevatlinan kala. We still have to deal with
the reality of
the perception, the perception of the reality and the reality of the
perception. So what are we going to do? There's a perception she's
married to ראובן Reuven and now we saw she got married to
שמעון. Shimon So one opinion is that ראובן Reuven is, we're going
to force ראובן Reuven to divorce her, but
we will not allow for the option of שמעון Shimon. divorcing her
because it'll look like מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. And the second opinion,
which according to תוספות' Tosafos way we פסקן pasken like, is we're
not concerned about a perception of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. You know,
again, it's unfortunate to any degree that we have to accommodate the
perception of the reality. We're not concerned, we'll let her go back
to ראובן Reuven, if that's what works, or to go to ראובן
Reuven, if that's what works, because we'll say given that there was
a perception she was married to ראובן, Reuven people will just assume
the marriage to שמעון Shimon, never happened. Okay, wrapping this up. יצא
לה קול מזה ומזה מהו. Yatza lah kol mizeh umizeh mahu. Let's
say there was not that we know שמעון Shimon. married her, there
was a rumor that on Monday, a strong rumor on Monday she
got married to ראובן, Reuven and then another rumor on Tuesday, a
strong rumor she got married to שמעון. Okay? So there's just two
competing rumors. What's the story there? You know, these again are rumors
that we have to that apparently are strong enough we have to
be worried about. We'll assume we were not able to clarify their
truth or not. So what are her options that are available to
her now? רב פפא אמר אף זו מגרש ראשון ונושא שני. Rav
Papa amar af zu megarish rishon venosei sheini. Even this one she's
limited. If you follow רב הונא, within רב הונא, she's limited to
the same possibilities. She has to go back to, she has to
stay with שמעון, otherwise it'll look like
מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. ואשמימר אמר מותרת לשניהם. V'ashmeimar amar muteres lishneihem.
No, Ashmeimar says, no, come on. At this point already even רב
הונא would agree we're not going to limit her options. Okay? Since
both of them are rumors, we're not going to be concerned that
they're going to say rumor number one was definitely true and rumor
number two was definitely true, and she was married and divorced and
remarried and re-divorced and so on. No, since it's all rumor, we'll
let her stay with ראובן Reuven, and we'll assume that you know
only one of the rumors had to be false in order for
her to be able to stay with ראובן and it not be
מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. והלכתא מותרת לשניהם. Vehilchasa muteres lishneihem. That's the
way we פסקן. If it's just competing rumors, yes, we do have
to attend to them, but we're not going to give both of
them such absolute weight that we're going to be concerned of a
perception of מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso and we will allow her to
stay married with ראובן, get a גט get from שמעון. Again, all
of this though does remain unfortunate, especially if you פסקן לא מבטלינן
קלא, lo mevatlinan kala, that even when we know the facts, we
have to to some degree accommodate the perception. Okay, now we pick
up last דף, daf, top of צדי עמוד א. tzadi amud aleph.
And after all an entire מסכת maseches that deals with the technicality
or the legal act of the actual legal act of divorce and
the writing of the גט and so on, we finally get to
a משנה mishnah that deals with the circumstances which warrant a divorce.
בית שמאי
אומרים לא יגרש אדם את אשתו אלא אם כן מצא בה דבר
ערוה, Beis Shammai omrim lo yegaresh adam es ishto ela im kein
matza bah devar ervah, שנאמר כי מצא בה ערות דבר. shene'emar ki
matza bah ervas davar. Okay, so the פסוק pasuk that talks about
divorce says, you know, it's actually funny, the whole תורה Torah where
it talks about giving the גט and whatever, וכתב לה ספר כריתות,
vechasav lah sefer krisus, sort of talks about it almost like in
passing, oh a man finds his wife ערות דבר, ervas davar, an
act of sexual sin, ויהי אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו, vayehi im
lo timtza chen b'einav, she doesn't find favor. even as he's כי
מצא בה ערוות דבר ki matza bah ervas davar and he divorces
her and then another man marries her and oh then don't the
first guy can't remarry her. Like it's all in the context of
the איסור issur of מחזיר גרושתו, machzir grushaso, the whole תורה's Torah
what it has to say about גט and divorce is sort of
a you know sort of within the framing of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir
grushaso. Be that as it may, okay, it frames the initial circumstances
why the first guy divorced her, והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו
v'hayah im lo timtza chen be'einav she doesn't find favor in his
eyes כי מצא בה ערוות דבר. ki matza bah ervas davar. So
בית שמאי Beit Shammai focuses on מצא בה ערוות דבר matza bah
ervas davar that there was actually a matter of sexual sin, and
it could mean suspected of sexual sin, but it seems like מצא
בה matza bah and the language of the גמרא Gemara, is going
to sound like no, he actually knows that she committed adultery. So
the only time that the תורה Torah sort of warrants divorce, and
we'll see about the בדיעבד in the גמרא, Gemara is according to
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is when he's forced to divorce her, when
there's actually an act of adultery. Otherwise, there's no basis for divorce.
אלא אם כן מצא בה דבר ערווה שנאמר כי מצא בה ערוות
דבר. ella im ken matza bah devar ervah shenne'emar ki matza bah
ervas davar. Now the לא יגרש את אדם, lo yegaresh et adam,
a person should not, already from the משנה Mishna it is very
much suggests that it's a question about guidelines and what is appropriate
and nobody is questioning the fact that the גט actually works. Right?
This would be in general within you know the תורה Torah within
הלכה, halacha, the גט while it does require עדים, eidim, doesn't require
a בית דין and really is in a way a you know
an act between the two parties, between the husband and wife. This
is different than a you know this is different than the idea
of of that a court issues a divorce and or fault and
no-fault divorce where the state has to decide whether the state will
issue a divorce under these circumstances. And in cases in which there's
fault divorce, you know if you don't have justifying circumstances, you're just
never going to have a divorce that is going to be given
by the state. That is not what we are saying here. Here
the it's like a type of a almost transaction, obviously it affects
status, but it's between the two of them, it does not have
to be warranted, it does not have to be approved of by
by the state. And therefore the question of motivation you know is
being framed here very much in terms of a guidelines and what
is appropriate not actually what is required for the divorce to be
binding. Okay, but בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, still is coming from
that attitude of fault divorce, you should not get divorced unless there's
absolutely no other alternative, the woman actually committed adultery which הלכתית halachically
makes it forbidden for them to be living together, שנאמר כי מצא
בה ערוות דבר. shenne'emar ki matza bah ervat davar. בית הלל אומרים
Beit Hillel omrim אפילו הקדיחה תבשילו, afilu hikdicha tavshilo, even if she
just burned his soup, his you know his porridge, רש"י Rashi says
even it means put in too many spices or it means it
actually burnt it, did just something that annoyed him, שנאמר כי מצא
בה ערוות דבר. shenne'emar ki matza bah ervat davar. Now of course
it's the exact same פסוק, pasuk, but as we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara. they emphasize the word דבר, Davar מצא בה דבר, matza
bah davar, there was something that you didn't like, some little thing
that upset the guy. Okay, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai says there
needs to be very little justification. בית הלל, Beit Hillel, which is
interesting, you know we often think that בית הלל Beit Hillel is
לקולא, lekula,
is he being, I mean if you think about that the wife
wants to stay married and the husband is acting capriciously and so
on, if that genuinely is the dynamic, then then that's certainly not
being sensitive to the wife. On the other hand, it certainly is
lenient in the sense of giving a wide berth of human freedom,
right? That you don't you're not restricted in terms of that. And
also, you know, it also you know the it also maybe the
wife is the one that wants to get the divorce and so
on, of course that's not how all this is all framed, this
is all very unilateral from the perspective of the husband. But the
point is is that when you anyway do not have the בית
שמאי Beit Shammai parameters, you're giving it is a קולא. kula. Might
have harmful consequences to people, but you're a קולא kula at least
in the sense that you're operating with fewer restrictions. Okay, but רבי
עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, אפילו מצא
אחרת נאה ממנה, afilu matza acheret na'ah mimenna, שנאמר והיה אם לא
תמצא חן בעיניו. shenne'emar v'hayah im lo timtza chen be'einav. She doesn't
have to have done anything wrong, you don't even have to think
she's done anything wrong, she's the perfect wife, but this guy all
of a sudden he's more attracted to some you know to a
secretary 20 years younger, that's enough, she doesn't have to she could
be the perfect wife and done everything
right but והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו, v'hayah im lo timtza
chen be'einav, you no longer find favor in my eyes, I'm now
attracted to somebody else. Again, very, very harsh in terms of thinking
about anything to protect the interest of the wife. Now again, this
is all about guidelines, this is not about legal restrictions about when
a גט can be good or not, but nevertheless even as terms
of guidelines, is it a healthy thing for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
to be saying something of this nature? So you know, I mean
some people want to sort of connect this to the רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva who who is like one of the few תנאים Tannaim
or אמוראים Amoraim or whatever that we know in terms of his
like love affair with his wife. with his wife and how much
and how much he profoundly and deeply impassionedly fell in love with
her.
So maybe he just is a romantic and just believes
you have to go where your heart leads you and you should
always be passionately in love with your wife and therefore yes, that's
a basis for divorce.
Anyway, so but it's a little hard to read, I think we
do have to acknowledge,
and it does also connect with another position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in a number of places speaks
about the importance about a wife like washing herself or whatever on
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and so on and יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and
practices during נידה Niddah to make sure that a woman is not
תתגנה על בעלה, Titganeh Al Ba'alah, does not in any way become
displeasing to her husband because if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva follows an
approach
that
if a man should feel
is in his rights to feel that he wants to marry anybody,
a woman who he just is more attracted to or finds more
pleasing, right, then it puts a heavy sort of responsibility on his
wife to always be looking her best and always be having her
husband attracted to her. So it does lead to certain leniencies within
הלכה Halacha but again something to really think about in terms of
our contemporary ethos.
Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara תניא, Tanya,
תניא, Tanya, we turned a ברייתא. Braisa. אמר בית הלל לבית שמאי.
Amar Beis Hillel Le'Beis Shammai. בית הלל Beis Hillel said to בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, ולא כבר נאמר דבר? Velo Kvar Ne'emar Davar? It
says דבר Davar which means any matter, doesn't have to be ערוה.
Ervah. אמר להם בית שמאי, Amar Lahem Beis Shammai, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai said, ולא כבר נאמר ערות? Velo Kvar Ne'emar Ervat? But it
says ערות Ervat which means ערוה, Ervah, sexual sin. אמר להם בית
הלל אם נאמר ערות ולא נאמר דבר הייתי אומר משום ערות תצא
משום דבר לא תצא. Amar Lahem Beis Hillel Im Ne'emar Ervat Velo
Ne'emar Davar Hayisi Omer Mishum Ervat Tetzei Mishum Davar Lo Tetzei. No,
it had to say both. Okay, because it had to
say דבר Davar, not just ערות Ervat because if it said ערות
Ervat of course you can divorce your wife because of sexual sin,
but I might not have known that you could divorce her just
because of anything that bothered you, a דבר, Davar any small transgression
and not even transgression, any small misstep. לכך נאמר דבר. Lekach Ne'emar
Davar. It has to say no that there's an act that even
anything, even any matter that was wrong. ואילו נאמר דבר ולא נאמר
ערות הייתי אומר משום דבר תינשא לאחר משום ערוה לא תינשא לאחר.
Ve'ilu Ne'emar Davar Velo Ne'emar Ervat Hayisi Omer Mishum Davar Tinaseh Le'Acher
Mishum Ervah Lo Tinaseh Le'Acher. The next part of the פסוק Pasuk
when it says והלכה והייתה לאיש אחר. Ve'halcha Ve'haysa Le'ish Acher. I
might have thought okay if it had just said if a man
divorces his wife because he doesn't like her she can marry somebody
else I might have thought okay, but if he divorces her because
she actually committed a sexual sin, committed adultery, maybe she's not entitled
to marry somebody else. Now the הלכה Halacha is she can't marry
the adulterer, but she can marry anybody any other person. לכך נאמר
ערות, Lekach Ne'emar Ervat, therefore it has to say both. It has
to say that even when there's adultery she's permitted to marry someone
else but in terms of justifications for divorce even the slightest thing.
ובית שמאי, U'Beis Shammai, so that's the double language. Now for בית
שמאי Beis Shammai now the question is why does it say דבר
Davar? which is בית הלל's Beis Hillel basis of saying even a
small thing? Why didn't it just say כי מצא בה ערות? Ki
Matza Bah Ervat? So בית שמאי האי דבר מאי עביד ליה? Beis
Shammai Hai Davar Mai Avid Lei?
What would they do with דבר? Davar נאמר כאן דבר ונאמר להלן
דבר על פי שנים עדים או על פי שלשה עדים יקום דבר.
Ne'emar Kan Davar Ve'ne'emar Le'alan Davar Al Pi Shnayim Eidim O Al
Pi Shlosha Eidim Yakum Davar. A matter shall be established by two
or three witnesses. מה להלן בשני עדים אף כאן בשני עדים. Ma
Le'alan Bishnei Eidim Af Kan Bishnei Eidim. To tell you that the
same way you need two witnesses to testify in a court case,
if you want to prove a woman's infidelity and adultery, right, so
she's suspected and then it's only through a particular process, but for
a woman to be seen as having committed adultery even not to
punish her in court, but in terms of creating an obligation forbidden
for a husband to live with her and an obligation to get
divorced, that has to be with witnesses. ובית הלל מי כתיב ערוה
בדבר? U'Beis Hillel Mi Ksiv Ervah Bi'davar? It didn't say an ערוה
Ervah was found through דבר Davar through witnesses, it says ערות דבר.
Ervat Davar. So דבר Davar. is not the witnessing, it's a separate
thing. ובית שמאי מי כתיב או ערוה או דבר? U'Beis Shammai Mi
Ksiv O Ervah O Davar? בית שמאי Beis Shammai says okay, but
let's face it, ערות דבר Ervat Davar is a single phrase, it's
not two things, ערוה Ervah or דבר. Davar ובית הלל הכי כתיב
ערות דבר דמשמע הכי ומשמע הכי. Ve'Hillel Hachi Ksiv Ervat Davar Di'mashmach
Hachi U'mashmach Hacha. Yes, you're right, it's a phrase and therefore it's
telling you both. It's telling you either you can divorce for ערוה
Ervah or divorce for דבר Davar and oh by the way in
terms of evidence of adultery that needs to be with witnesses. Okay
fine, but for בית שמאי Beis Shammai again this is why it
seems that the ערוה Ervah is not just suspicion of adultery and
so on
or sexual impropriety, since they're using דבר davar they're really learning this
to tell you that that this woman has actually committed adultery and
that's when divorce is warranted. Again it'll work even not that way
but that's when it's warranted when there's real evidence of adultery and
there's absolute, it's actually Halakhically forbidden to stay married, that is the
case one case that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says where divorce is
really warranted. Okay now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבי עקיבא אומר אפילו
מצא אחר נאה הימנה. Rabbi Akiva Omer Afilu Matza Acher Na'eh Mimena.
Even another one more beautiful. or just more pleasing. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai
kamifalgi? What's their debating? So, and the גמרא Gemara is now asking
this in a technical sense, not in a more sort of attitude
towards marriage and divorce sense. אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Reish Lakish. They
argue about with the in the position of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish.
דאמר ריש לקיש כי משמש בד' לשונות. De'amar Reish Lakish ki mishamesh
b'arba leshonot. אי דילמא אלא דהא. Ee dilma ela de'ha. The word
כי ki in the Torah can operate in four ways. It can
mean 'if', it can mean
'lest', אלא ela rather, and דהא de'ha because. Rashi has a lot
of examples, but one cute example where you have both is by
אברהם Avraham and שרה. Sarah. It says
that שרה Sarah says לא צחקתי כי יראתי lo tzakhati ki yareti
because she said she did not laugh because, כי, ki, she was
afraid.
ויאמר אברהם לא כי צחקת Vayomer Avraham lo ki tzakhat you did.
So that is כי ki meaning דהא de'ha because she was afraid
and אלא rather.
אי ei if like is like כי תראה שור שנאך. ki tir'eh
shor sona'akha. If you see the ox of your enemy. כי ki
is very often כי יקרא קן ציפור לפניך. ki yikarei kan tzippor
lefaneikha. אי. ei. דילמא dilma lest is כי תאמר בלבבך ki tomar
bilvavekha lest you say in your heart רבים הגוים האלה ממני. rabbim
hagoyim ha'eileh mimmenni. There are actually more than just those four. But
anyway. So now how do they debate that? בית שמאי סברי, Beit
Shammai savri, בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds, והיה אם לא תמצא
חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר דהא מצא בה ערות דבר.
ve'hayah im lo timtza hen be'einav ki matza bah ervat davar de'ha
matza bah ervat davar. It's one statement. Why does she not find
favor? Because she has committed adultery. So really it is only one
option here, she's committed adultery. רבי עקיבא סבר כי מצא בה ערות
דבר אי נמי מצא בה ערות דבר. Rabbi Akiva savar ki matza
bah ervat davar ee nami matza bah ervat davar. No, they're two
separate things. והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו ve'hayah im lo timtza
hen be'einav if she does not find favor, כי מצא בה ערות
דבר ki matza bah ervat davar if he found a matter of
ערוה. ervah. Obviously that's still a little funny that the
o doesn't seem normally how the כי ki would mean the word
o, but anyway he reads those as two separate statements. Fine. אמר
ליה רב פפא לרבא. Amar leih Rav Pappa le'Rava. Now, actually also
בית שמאי Beit Shammai also, sorry, בית הלל Beit Hillel also is
like בית שמאי Beit Shammai that does not see והיה אם לא
תמצא חן בעיניו ve'hayah im lo timtza hen be'einav as a separate
clause.
And it's only רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who sees it as completely
independent. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא. Amar leih Rav Pappa le'Rava. לא
מצא בה לא ערוה ולא דבר מאי? Lo matza bah lo ervah
velo davar mai? If let's say
there was no basis, no ערוה, ervah, no דבר according to בית
הלל Beit Hillel or בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, he divorced and he
divorced her without these justifying sort of motivations, does it work or
does he have to remarry her? אמר ליה, Amar leih, he said
to him, דגלי רחמנא גבי אונס. degali Rachmana gabei ones. Since the
Torah says by the rapist, לא יוכל לשלחה כל ימיו. lo yukhal
leshalekhah kol yamav. He cannot divorce her all his life, which means
כל ימיו kol yamav בקום והחזר. bekum vehachzeir. If he divorces the
woman that he raped if she agrees to marry him that he's
not allowed to divorce her and if he divorces her he has
to remarry her.
בקום והחזר קאי. Bekum vehachzeir ka'ei. התם הוא דגלי רחמנא. Hatam hu
degali Rachmana. So there by the rapist the Torah tells you he
has to remarry her. אבל הכא מאי דעבד עבד. Aval hacha mai
de'avad avad. Here maybe the Torah was not within the guidelines of
the Torah, but obviously as we said earlier it will take effect
regardless. This is not saying that the גט only works under these
circumstances.
אמר ליה רב משרשיא לרבא. Amar leih Rav Mesharshiya le'Rava. אם לבו
לגרשה והיא יושבת תחתיו ומשמשת מהו? Im libo le'gareshah ve'hi yoshevet tachtav
umeshamasht mihu? Let's say he is planning on divorcing her but he's
keeping it to himself until he is good and ready he's going
to have her in the house and making his meals and making
his bed and having sex with her and he's not telling her
that his plan is to divorce her. So like what's the story?
Obviously it's repugnant but he actually is looking for some type of
a statement to that effect.
קרי עליה, Karei aleih, he says the following פסוק pasuk applies: אל
תחרש על רעך רעה והוא יושב לבטח אתך. Al tacharosh al re'akha
ra'ah vehu yoshev lavetach itakh. Do not plot against your friend.
Like רעים האהובים. re'im ha'ahuvim. Right. This person who you're close to
do not plot against them evil והוא יושב לבטח אתך vehu yoshev
lavetach itakh and he is dwelling with surety with you. So it's
a tremendous sense of betrayal that you are going ahead and planning
this evil and working under these understandings of the relationship and taking
advantage and it's just tremendous betrayal to be doing something of this
nature. תניא. Tanya. We taught in a ברייתא. braita. היה רבי מאיר
אומר: Hayah Rabbi Meir omer: כשם שהדעות במאכל כך דעות בנשים. Keshem
she'hade'ot bama'akhal kakh de'ot benashim. The same way there are different attitudes
towards food, there's different attitudes towards women. Often food and sex are
used as an analogy here. It's less about sex per se, but
anyway let's see what this analogy is. יש לו לאדם שזבוב נופל
לתוך כוסו וזורקו ואינו שותהו. Yesh lo le'adam she'zvuv nofel letoch koso
vezorko ve'eino shotehu. A
certain person is very finicky, fastidious, a fly falls into his cup
of wine and he throws out the whole cup of wine, it's
been a tiny bit contaminated, he won't drink it.
וזו היא מדת פפוס בן יהודה. Vezu hi middat Pappos ben Yehuda.
when comparing this to men's attitudes towards their wives—again, very thin ice
here about, in general, the whole sense about eating, easy disposal of
wives, the nice thing about בית שמאי—I Beit Shammai mean okay, it's
very restrictive, but it certainly means that the husband cannot just treat
his wife as something that he can dispose of as soon as
it a little bit annoys him. Okay. And but the idea that
a man can unilaterally divorce his wife, and that creates a certain
type of potential way of looking at this relationship, to property, as
if to food and so on, there's obviously going on here in
this analogy. So here, the comparison would be שהיה
נועל בפני אשתו ויוצא. shehaya noel bifnei ishto veyotzei. When he would
leave his house, he would lock the door and keep his wife
locked up in jail in the house, which is horrific. And he
would be so fastidious, the same way he wouldn't drink wine that
a fly touched, he wouldn't want to be with his wife, have
sex with his wife or whatever the case, that she had any
interaction with the outside world. Obviously, as רש"י Rashi points out how
bad that is, if you look at the last line of רש"י,
Rashi, ומידה שאינה הוגנת היא זו שמתוך כך איבה נכנסת ביניהם ומזנה
תחתיו. umida sheina hogenet hi zo shemitoch kach eiva nichneset beineihem umezana
tachtav. That he's thinking that he's totally protecting her from whatever, from
this, but actually that just creates terrible hatred and enmity and suspicion
and jealousy and it just leads to much, much worse results. That
she would even go ahead and דווקא davka commit adultery. But even
that point aside, obviously it's horrific for us to think about this
type of a controlling relationship. And we know about spousal abuse and
so on. Anyway, and the גמרא Gemara is looking at it as
not looking at it through that lens at all. Obviously it might
be critical of this, but it's just that he's overly fastidious, he
doesn't want his wife interacting with anyone.
Okay.
וזו מידת כל אדם. vezo midat kol adam. Okay. יש
לך אדם שזבוב נופל לתוך כוסו. yesh lecha adam shezvuv nofel letoch
koso. There's somebody else that the fly falls into his
cup, וזורקו ושותהו, vezorko veshotehu, and you get rid of the fly
and drink the cup. Like two second rule, three second rule. וזוהי
מידת כל אדם. vezohei midat kol adam. That's the way most people
are with their food and with their wives. שמדברת עם אחיה וקרוביה,
shemedaberet im acheia vekroveia,
that she speaks, she interacts with other possible things that can contaminate,
right, her brother, her friend, ומניחה, umanicha, and he allows it. He's
not concerned that that's somehow, he doesn't get suspicious about jealous and
other types of things. ויש לך אדם שזבוב נופל לתוך תמחוי. veyesh
lecha adam shezvuv nofel letoch tamchuy. And then there's somebody that the
fly falls into the stew. It's interesting now that it switches to
the stew. מוצצו ואוכלו. motzetzo veochlo. And he rings out the fly
to get all the juices of the stew out of the fly
and then he goes and eats it. Not the fly, the stew.
זוהי מידת אדם רע. zohei midat adam ra. That's even after things
have really been contaminated. Maybe the stew gets more contaminated than the
wine. He,
it doesn't bother him. שרואה את אשתו יוצאת וראשה פרוע. sheroe et
ishto yotzet verosha parua. His wife goes out and acts in this
very free manner that maybe allows,
wanting to attract attention or not, but she just goes out in
this way that's not modest and that draws the other eyes of
men. יוצאת וראשה פרוע. yotzet verosha parua. She goes out with her
head uncovered. וטווה בשוק. vetova bashuk. And she knits in the marketplace,
exposing her arms. ופרומה משני צדדיה. ufruma mishnei tzadadeiha. She wears clothing
that is slit up the side.
ורוחצת עם בני אדם. verochetzet im bnei adam. And bathes with men.
עם בני אדם סלקא דעתך? im bnei adam salka datcha? The גמרא
Gemara says literally with men? I mean oh my
God, who would do that, right? A woman bathing together with men?
She's presumably anywhere probably naked.
אלא במקום שבני אדם רוחצין. ela bemakom shebnei adam rochtzin. Okay fine,
but in the same place in the river where the men would
bathe. So she's going in while they're going out or vice versa,
way too close. זו מצווה מן התורה לגרשה. zo mitzva min hatora
legarsha. This type of a case where a woman is acting this
way, it's a mitzvah to divorce her. Whether because not necessarily because
there's direct suspicion that she committed adultery, but just because that is,
this is a whole discussion in כתובות Ketubot about דת משה Dat
Moshe and דת יהודית Dat Yehudit and a certain way of acting
that within the context of a marriage. It's true
the משנה Mishna talks specifically about women's behavior, we would talk about
both, is a husband supposed to go flirting with every waitress when
they go down, when they're at a restaurant? There's ways in which
you act that
are inappropriate in terms of acting with people that are not your
spouse or drawing attention from people that are not your spouse. So
this is a מצווה לגרשה, mitzva legarsha, שנאמר כי מצא. sheneemar ki
matza. מצא בה ערות דבר ושלחה מביתו והלכה והיתה לאיש אחר. matza
bah ervas davar veshilchah mibeito vehalcha vehayta l'ish acher. There's something מצא
בה ערות דבר matza bah ervas davar and here I think it's
reading ערות דבר ervas davar and again not evidence of adultery but
that ערות דבר ervas davar in a more broad sense.
So you know, inappropriate, inappropriate behavior of a sexual nature. Okay.
Now, now we're going to continue explaining this פסוק pasuk that says
והיתה לאיש אחר vehayta l'ish acher so this woman who's divorced and
let's say it means not for this reason, let's say it means,
you know, ממש mamash adultery or one of the other, okay, she
goes marries another one. הכתוב קראו אחר, hakatuv kera'o acher, a different
man.
לומר שאין זה בן זוגו לראשון. lomar she'ein ze ben zugo larishon.
The second guy is not a twin with the first guy in
the negative sense. Okay. זה, ze, the first guy did the right
thing. הוציא רשע מביתו, hotzi rasha mibeito, he got rid of this
wicked woman from his house, this woman who acts in this very
sexually free manner in public, okay, or actually committed adultery. וזה, veze,
the other guy is an אחר, acher, he's different, he's not of
the same quality as the first guy. הכניס רשע לתוך ביתו, hichnis
rasha letoch beito, he brings her into her house. Again, this is
all very, very much from the male eye, the male perspective, and
there is so much to sort of, you know, say about this
and about how things could very much, you know, when men control
women and they have their and suspicions and so on and men's
behavior,
etc. But anyway, we'll continue.
וזכה שני שלח. vezacha sheni shelakh. If the second guy merits, he'll
also divorce her because he shouldn't have married her in the first
place. שנאמר ושנאה האיש האחרון. shenemar vesane'ah ha'ish ha'acharon. Okay, and then
the פסוק pasuk says and what happens if the second guy hates
her and divorces her? ואם לא, ve'im lo, but if he's not
that meritorious, קברתהו, kevertahu, she'll bury him. שנאמר או כי ימות האיש
האחרון shenemar o ki yamut ha'ish ha'acharon or he dies. Okay, so
this guy really should have known better than to marry her. כדאי
הוא במיתה, kedai hu bemitah, he is, you know, death is fitting
for him. שזה הוציא רשע מביתו וזה הכניס רשע לתוך ביתו. sheze
hotzi rasha mibeito veze hichnis rasha letoch beito. In case we didn't
get it the first time, the first, you know, this is a
deserving end because the first guy got this wicked woman out of
his house and this guy brought her into his house.
Now, last little דרשה drasha on this idea. כי שנא שלח, ki
sane shalakh, when you hate, divorce, send away.
רבי יהודה אומר אם שנאתה שלח, Rabbi Yehuda omer im senitah shalakh,
if you hate her, send her away. So this is, now רש"י
Rashi says כרבי עקיבא, keRabbi Akiva, that's like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
You hate her. I don't know if רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says who says לא תמצא חן בעיניו lo
timtza chen be'einav is the same as saying that she's hated. I
mean, it is true that לאה Leah is called שנואה, senu'ah, you
know, but anyway, but anyway, so that's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or
maybe it's רב בית הלל, Rav Beit Hillel, okay, when you don't
like her, you get rid of her. רבי יוחנן אומר שנוי המשלח.
Rabbi Yochanan omer sanui hamishale'ach. No, no, no, the one who sends
her out is to be hated. You know, that's a more of
a, you know, בית שמאי Beit Shammai type of a thing of
an approach. Like, you do not just trivially divorce your wife. There's
a different גירסא girsa if you do, you are considered to be
despicable. Okay, there's a different גירסא girsa on the side.
שנואה היא לפני המקום שלח. snu'ah hi lifnei hamakom shalakh. Only when
she is hated by God should you send her out, meaning only
if she committed adultery. So it's a sort of a רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, בית שמאי Beit Shammai or בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית
שמאי Beit Shammai different ways of reading the פסוק. pasuk. ולא פליגי,
velo pligi, the גמרא Gemara says in a way they don't disagree.
הא בזוג ראשון הא בזוג שני. ha bezug rishon ha bezug sheni.
It depends whether it is the first marriage or the second marriage.
דאמר רבי אלעזר כל המגרש אשתו ראשונה אפילו מזבח מוריד עליו דמעות.
de'amar Rabbi Elazar kol hamigaresh ishto rishonah afilu mizbe'ach morid alav dma'ot.
Any man who divorces his first wife, even the altar cries, you
know, that this, that the tragedy of it.
שנאמר וזאת שנית תעשו כסות דמעה את מזבח ה' בבכי ואנקה. shenemar
vezot shenit ta'asu kessut dim'ah et mizbe'ach Hashem bevchi ve'anaka. Cover the
altar of God with crying and with wailing. מאין עוד פנות אל
המנחה ולקחת רצון מידכם me'ein od pnot el hamincha velakachat ratzon miyedchem
because God is no longer turning to the מנחה mincha and wants
to accept this from your hands. ואמרתם על מה ve'amartem al mah
and you say why? What have we done wrong? That the crying
is covering the altar and God no longer is desirous of us.
על כי ה' העיד בינך ובין אשת נעוריך אשר אתה בגדתה בה
al ki Hashem he'id beincha uvein eshet ne'urecha asher ata bagadta bah
because God is testifying about you and the wife of your youth
that you have betrayed. והיא חברתך ואשת בריתך, vehi chavertech ve'eshet britecha,
she is your, your, your friend, your, you know, your soulmate
and the woman of your covenant. And therefore, how could you do
this terrible thing? Now, obviously, that our relationship with God is ruptured
when we rupture our relationship with our spouses, and even the altar
here, the image of the altar crying. And what the גמרא is
saying is, is that to divorce the first, you know, marriage, you
know, that is sort of seen as, you know, like the, you
know, just the foundational, the one that we hope will be forever,
like,
and for that to end in divorce is a real, real tragedy,
and that is something that. If it were less than an extremely
justifying reason, you know, like an ערבת דבר, Ervat Davar, that would
be something in which that would be seen as a total tragedy
and the altar would cry and the person, the man who did
it without a good enough reason should be considered hateful or despicable
and so on. That is where we sort of apply more of
a בית שמאי Beit Shammai ethos, maybe not exactly, but we just
see don't do it for trivial reasons, you know,
and when we sort of speak maybe more about, you know, it
doesn't have to be the worst, you know, like, like ערבת דבר,
Ervat Davar, it doesn't have to be adultery, there could be other
reasons and so on, maybe that's in a case of a second
marriage. Now again, there's something very beautiful about this and about the
imagery and so on, but, you know, it does worth ending this
by saying, you know, and there recently I think it was just
a posting I saw an op-ed in Times of Israel about a
woman, a פרום frum woman who went through the whole divorce process
and the way in which, you know, the rabbis are just so
horrific, you know, in terms of how they deal both with the
man and the woman, let alone opening the door for a man
to extort the wife, you know, and so on. But, but, you
know, people go through a very long and well-thought-out process and they
decide, you know, and want to get divorced and so on, and
after much, you know, many, many steps in the procedure and they
finally come before the בית דין and then the way the rabbis
just, you know, make them feel horrific that they're there and that
they're even thinking about it and so on. I mean, sometimes divorce
is the right decision, you know. So, so the finding that right
balance between don't do it trivially and at the same time, you
know, don't create these enormous obstacles and saying only in, you know,
cases of adultery or whatever, you know,
you have to find the right sort of balance between the sort
of what's being, you know, expressed here and and the realities of
life. The final thing maybe to end with is the word about
חברתך ואשת בריתך, Chavrat'cha v'Eshet Beritecha, which is actually very beautiful and
speaks about the partnership even though some of the end here and
a lot of the מסכת masechet is about the husband sort of
like unilateral ability, you know, within the area of divorce and power
and maybe even sometimes treating her like property and all of this
whole discussion that we just had, saying like your, your friend and
the wife of your covenant, the woman of your covenant is a
very equal partnership type of an image, and it's actually interesting that
in some כתובות ketubot that were found in the Cairo גניזה, Geniza,
they use exactly this phrase describing the marriage, you know, you know,
אשתי ואשת בריתי, ishti v'eshet briti, חברתי ואשת בריתי, chaverti v'eshet briti,
so that's a very nice note on which to end this מסכת.
masechet.